Jan2010 Integration Branch Help

Plan:

[DONE] Jits to merge Eric's branch into a new branch (integration-jan10) with Eric's help.

[DONE] Jits to then merge Mannie's branch into integration branch.

We then ALL work off this integration branch.

We set up a solid testing framework (mocha, factory girl, rspec, cucumber etc)

We write loads of tests.

We finish all new work and make it production ready.

We merge into trunk.

Service Overall Status Algorithm

ignore all ServiceTests NOT run by the BioCatalogue

for all ServiceTests that are run by the BioCatalogue, go through the latest TestResult

if there are none, status is “blue”

if at least one has failed, status is “amber” and relevant failure messages should be appended to the overal status message

if all tests pass then status is “green”

To use the Integration Branch do :

Checkout the new integration-jan2010 branch

Set up config files

Note especially that you SHOULD create a new biocat_local.rb file from the template in the repository. Some initialization constants have been renamed.

Make sure the namespace sections in the memcache.yml are different to everything else and unique per environment (to prevent cache clashes)

Set up a separate dev database just for this integration branch work. Use the latest data snapshot in the BioCatalogue folder in DropBox.

Note that the test_results table is missing. So you need to go into the schema_migrations tables and delete the entry with the “version” value “20090517060157”, and then run db:migrate.

Set up a separate, EMPTY test database just for this integration branch work

Run rake db:migrate

Don't eat yellow snow

Running the embrace import

Get the latest services.xml, tags.xml and users.xml from Dropbox BioCatalogue/Embrace/ImportData

Create a directory in application root called 'embrace' and put these import files in there

Turn off mailing from the application. This should only be switched on on live site. All test & development environments should turn off mailing by default

Turn off tweeting.

run

script/biocatalogue/embrace_import.rb -e <environment> 

Date: Monday 19 July 2010

Time: 15:00-16:00 (UK)

Telcon No: 08444737630

Pin: 70503011

Attending

Manchester: Carole, Jits, Mannie, Franck

EBI: Eric, Rodrigo, Hamish

Apologies

Agenda

Actions from the last telcon

Report from ISMB

Report from IEEE conference

Daily operations Report

Review of public wiki and public facing material

Review of Roadmap

Planning of next release

Actions from Previous Meeting

Jits, Eric: Contributors license for BioCatalogue… ongoing

Franck: Organise next SAB meeting. Possibly end of September 2010… ongoing October might be a better date

Upcoming Meetings

Minutes

Report from ISMB

Demo and presentation went well. A lot of interest in the BioCatalogue. We should now focus on analysis of the content and a SPARQL endpoint for the BioCatalogue

Report from IEEE conference

Presentation of the Functional Unit went well, now need to focus on the implementation.

Daily operations Report

New members joining the BioCatalogue.

Lots of dead INB services.

the site was a bit slow but it's now fine

Review of public wiki and public facing material

We need a new template for the wiki but because EBI is moving to drupal we might as well wait to avoid doing it twice.

Sustainability of the BioCatalogue

Carole talking to Pistoia and PFIZER about the content curation

BioCatalogue has been proposed as a ELIXIR node.

We might consider include BioCatalogue as part of the apache foundation

New actions

Jits to recycle Taverna CLA for BioCatalogue ongoing … we'll reuse the Taverna one. EBI is ok with that.

Rodrigo to check if there are any contributions license at the EBI we need to consider … ongoing

Jits: send Emory contact details to Carole. Done

Rodrigo to check if we can get some money from the EBI to organise next SAB f2f…ongoing

Franck: Take a look at INB services and archive the dead ones…ongoing

Rodrigo/Eric: Send EBI wiki template to Franck… ongoing

Rodrigo to handle BioXsD-EDAM contact… ongoing

Mannie to send the bulk annotation via spreadsheet tool to Hamish for testing… ongoing

Eric/Rodrigo to talk to the sys admin team at the EBI about the BioCatalogue back-end… ongoing

Previous meeting: Phone Conference Meeting on June 28 2010

Next meeting:

The BioCatalogue Roadmap for 2009

First quarter of 2009 (Jan - Mar)

Private pilot (private beta) - Basic SOAP services registration, discovery and annotation. Batch upload of soaplab services.

Advanced service discovery and filtering (I) - Sorting and filtering (by providers and services types) and more faceted browsing features. At a glance counts of annotations on services.

Service annotation support - Simple tagging and functional description of services, operations, their inputs and outputs. Support for service operation inputs and outputs examples. Support for comments and discussion threads about services. Annotation provided by submitters, providers, expert curators and automated agents.

REST services support (I) - Ability to register, describe and search for REST services in BioCatalogue.

Content acquisition (I) - Import Feta annotation. Providers, experts and users' service registration and annotation.

Second quarter of 2009 (Apr - Jun)

Public pilot (public beta) - First public release (at ISMB 09) - see BioCatalogue beta

Service monitoring - availability - We will regularly monitor services, by checking the host, endpoints, WSDL and so on.

Content acquisition (II) - EMBRACE registry content acquisition (initial). Scavenge services from SeekDa.

Advanced service discovery and filtering (II) - Filtering by tags, providers, submitters, service types, locations, and so on.

More metadata support - Ability to provide many different types of annotations to describe and categorise services.

Advanced search functionality (I) - Search takes into account synonyms (taken from an ontology) to provide more relevant results.

User interface improvements - To provide intuitive ways to submit, browse, discover and annotate services.

Favouriting - Favourite the services that you use or like the most.

Third quarter 2009 (Jul - Sep)

Content acquisition (II) - Full EMBRACE registry import.

Public APIs (I) - Basic RESTful APIs to BioCatalogue (mainly read).

Soaplab services support - Better support for Soaplab services

Better WSDL parsing - Deeper parsing of WSDLs, including linked schemas which include more typed information on ports, inputs and outputs.

Better annotation and curation features (I) - annotations forms, in-situ annotating.

Content curation - Develop and improve tools for expert and community curation

Outreach -

Fourth quarter 2009 (Oct - Dec)

Service monitoring - testing - Test scripts to test out service functionality can be provided by submitters and service providers. We will then run these regularly to provide us with metrics on the availability/reliability. A traffic light system (red, green, amber) gives users an at-a-glance view on status.

Service changes monitoring - Monitoring changes in the WSDLs of services and updating the BioCatalogue records and providing a log of changes.

Final merge of the EMBRACE registry.

Better annotation and curation features (II) - Curation reports, Curation assertions and more improvements for expert/community curators as well as casual annotators.

REST services support (II) - Better support for REST services, with the ability to describe and annotate the exact Resources, Methods, Parameters and Representations of REST services.

Public APIs (II) - More functional RESTful APIs to BioCatalogue (read and write).

Active homepage - A more dynamic homepage with content on the latest things going on in the BioCatalogue (with news feeds, announcements, and so on).

Notifications and news feeds per service - RSS/ATOM feeds for services, providing information on all activity on a service within the BioCatalogue.

Better service availability reports - Including filtering by service availability and “at-a-glance” summary reports for curators.

Richer service provider profiles - Ability to add more details for service providers.

Richer user profiles - Ability to harvest your profile information from myExperiment.

Content acquisition (III) - Scavenge services from ProgrammableWeb, BioMOBY and more from SeekDa.

Annotation Jamboree! (I) - A community driven Web Service annotation event in Manchester.

Content curation - Ongoing curation of the content in the BioCatalogue.

Outreach

2010

Annotation Jamboree! (II) - possibly at ISMB '10

Integration with myExperiment - Services from BioCatalogue displayed in myExperiment so users of myExperiment can browse them.

Integration with Taverna - Ability to import Web Services and annotations to and from BioCatalogue and Taverna.

myBioCatalogue - Ability to set up your own local BioCatalogue registry.

Curation workbench/tools - New curation tools designed for expert curators.

“Try it now” service functionality - Ability to test and play with a service within the BioCatalogue interface before using it.

Semantic annotation support) - Ability to annotate service using ontologies and controlled vocabularies (possibly import/export semantically annotated services in different formats such as SAWSDL, SA-REST).

Advanced search functionality (II) - Similarity searches. Semantic search: search for services using terms from a defined ontology. Amazon-like search: people who searched for these also searched for those.

BioMoby and SADI services support - Better support for BioMoby and SADI services

Functional Unit of Services- Ability to present services in terms of their biological functions, biological data types and biological resources.

Agenda

1. Review documentation distributed from kick-off meeting and wiki, mailing lists and chats 2. Report on Pilot Scenario Use Case development

- Eric, Franck and Hamish on services to pilot with

- Eric and Franck on experiments with schema, models and

annotation migration

- User categories - Hamish

- Jits on implications to myExperiment for pilot

- Thomas and Rodrigo on first thoughts on a browser mockup

- All: writing up the Use Case and splitting into stories and tasks

3. Next steps on Scenario and timetable - producing BioCatalogue STORIES 4. Day to day management; chats etc 5. Meetings and deadlines that are coming up - for example the myExperiment backend 6. Sort out project name and logo 7. AOB

Attendees

EBI - Eric, Hamish,Rodrigo, Thomas.

Manchester - Carole,Franck,Jiten,Katy

Action Items

1) Action EBI - Register domain name “biocatalogue.org” and contact the Korean institute about “biocatalog.org”

2) Action Eric/Hamish/Thomas - Join the myexperiment skype chats

3) Action Eric/Franck - Produce matrix of service types against bioinformatics domain coverage and properties, to generate a representative set of services to pilot with.

4) Action Everybody - Dump all possible attributes/information that could be collected about services on to the mailing list in order to help Eric/Franck enhance the proposed curation model.

5) Action Jiten/Eric/Thomas - Setup a myExperiment environment at EBI and walk through myExperiment codebase.

6) Action everyone - Decide the exact date of the next telecom meeting; preferably week starting the 26/05.

7) Action Franck - select representative KEGG services to use.

8) Action Franck - send out definition of “semantic type” to mailing list for further discussion and refinement.

9) Action Eric/Franck - work on the metatada levels for bronze/silver/gold/platinum compliance. Notes

Agreed on BioCatalogue as the name and biocatalogue.org as the main domain name.

We discussed the need to set up the wiki properly with various sections (such as for meetings and resources).

Chats every other day on the myExp daily dev chats (4pm or 5pm). Would be very useful for at least Eric to sit in.

Eric and Franck have come up with a shortlist of services to pilot. They selected a range based on how widely used and the longevity of the providers.

Rodrigo was concerned about the volume of the soaplab services. Franck mentioned that about 90% have already been annotated and just need migration.

Modelling activity: Eric and Franck have produced a minimum data model. Have used them to annotate many different types of services.

Carole discussed the notion of bronze, silver, gold and platinum compliance, in terms of what level of annotations are provided. This fits in with the idea of “wheels” for each category of metadata, that shift according to what level of compliance (or change colour, or whatever).

Viewed mockups from Thomas - unanimous appreciation (both for quality of mockups and quality of sample data [of homeresque proportions]).

Discussed how to build the front end for the first pilot. Decided on building this within a myExperiment installation so we can explore close integration as well as leverage the existing platform. Thomas will spend time with Jits on setting everything up and familiarising with codebase.